<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Comics Dc on Matthew Phillips</title>
    <link>https://matthewphillips.info/categories/comics-dc.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Comics Dc on Matthew Phillips</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://matthewphillips.info/categories/comics-dc.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Batman: The Long Halloween</title>
      <link>https://matthewphillips.info/posts/batman-the-long-halloween.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matthewphillips.info/posts/batman-the-long-halloween.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Jeph Loeb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I flipped to the last page of The Long Halloween I had already decided that it was one of the best detective stories I had ever read. I had concluded that, in fact, it should be read in literature classes. Even after a couple of weeks to sit on it I can&amp;rsquo;t really back down from either of those statements. If any medium needs a signature piece, a piece to illustrate what makes the medium worthwhile, comics do, and Batman The Long Halloween could be that. This sounds hyperbolic, I know, and I do not mean to say that The Long Halloween is the best the medium has to offer; rather I am saying that it follows a familiar genre; one known in practically all fictional mediums, and it does so as well as the best of any other. And because of that it serves an exemplary comic book. That when you have a story as entralling as this, with art that perfectly complements it, you cannot put it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At it&amp;rsquo;s core Batman The Long Halloween is a three act detective story. In the first act there is the setup. Batman, who needs little introduction. The crime families of Gotham; The Falcones and the Maronis. Harvey Dent, district attourney. Catwoman. The commissioner, Jim Gordon. The second act comes quickly, as members of the crime families begin to be picked off. The third act comes unexpectedly at the end of the book, throwing a curveball at the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pace of the book is relentless. Each issue (except for a couple) revolves around a holiday and after the first couple the reader realizes that there will be a murder in each. This creates a rather intense sort of anxiety in the reader, who knows a murder is coming within only a handful of pages. If I were to criticize the pacing at all it is that the pacing, which no doubt was done to fit with the theme of each issue representing a separate holiday, makes it more difficult to appreciate Batman as a detective. There aren&amp;rsquo;t enough pages to contain both the movement of the plot forward, the profoundly interesting supporting case, and Batman making progress on the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that it matters, however, as this is a whodunnit where you don&amp;rsquo;t care so much about whodunnit. That might be the least interesting part about The Long Halloween. What makes this a defining piece of comic book literature is the world building done by Loeb right from the beginning. From the beginning it feels like you are dropped into Godfather, except with tights and psychotic characters. And at the same time it&amp;rsquo;s as noir as a comic book gets. That Loeb was able to pull those three genres together; noir, gangster, and superhero, together into a seemless, liveable, world is particularly amazing. It&amp;rsquo;s the thing that keeps you glued from the beginning to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As great as the book is, it&amp;rsquo;s not quite perfect. There are elements that didn&amp;rsquo;t have me on the edge of my seat. For example, although the crime family drama was interesting, I can&amp;rsquo;t point to any of the characters that I found particularly interesting on their own. In fact, I can&amp;rsquo;t really remember much about the characters at all. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t, I don&amp;rsquo;t think, point to any weakness of the characters, but probably rather that I&amp;rsquo;m just not that big of a fan of the crime family genre. For many this won&amp;rsquo;t be an issue, but for me it meant I had to keep notes in order to keep track of what was going on, and who might be Holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve read many who think that Tim Sale&amp;rsquo;s artwork in this book is an example of a book that thrives despite subpar art, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t disagree more. There is definitely a lack of symmetry in the art, but I don&amp;rsquo;t consider that to be a weakness at all. It is fitting with the gritty narrative. A polished looking character doesn&amp;rsquo;t belong in the world Loeb has created here. There still is an incredible amount of detail in the art. It&amp;rsquo;s just a little crooked, that&amp;rsquo;s all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being one of the only Batman classics I&amp;rsquo;ve read, I don&amp;rsquo;t have the perspective to talk about Harvey Dent&amp;rsquo;s transformation in the light of the history of the character. So I have to approach it as though it is his origin story (although I know that it is not). But from that perspective it&amp;rsquo;s still a fascinating look at a character who breaks down at the weight of events that surround him. Harvey is part of the triumvirate of Batman, Gordon, and himself. He feels the pressure to live up to his peers, and at the same time he is the public face for what is happening in Gotham. He feels a religious need to bring order to a city that has lost it. And it is that pressure that, or so we are led to believe, causes him to snap and become Holiday. The truth, as we find out, is that Harvey isn&amp;rsquo;t Holiday. Or at least, he&amp;rsquo;s not Holiday all on his own. He also had his wife paying a role as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have trouble coming to terms with his wife as being in on the act. We are not given a reason for her to become a killer. It feels, rather, that Loeb wanted a good twist and this provided one. Dent was a suspect from the early chapters and it would be too easy to have him be the lone perpetrator. Never the less, these are all minor quibbles. The book succeeds due to it&amp;rsquo;s amazing pacing, wide and layered cast, and world building. As a representative of the best of comic books it would make great learning material in schools, and as a comic fan it&amp;rsquo;s something you are missing out on if you haven&amp;rsquo;t read.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catwoman Volume 2: No Easy Way Down</title>
      <link>https://matthewphillips.info/posts/catwoman-volume-2-no-easy-way-down.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://matthewphillips.info/posts/catwoman-volume-2-no-easy-way-down.html</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Ed Brubaker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally picked up this trade on a whim, seeing it on the shelf at my LCS. I have long liked the Catwoman character, but in all the times when I tried out her ongoing I usually found it to be wanting. I suppose I had written off the series as being too low-priority for DC. Boy was I wrong. Had I known how fantastic this series would be I would have probably picked up the first trade before going for volume 2. Not to worry, I now have that one as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brubaker has a much different take on the character than anything I&amp;rsquo;ve read or seen before. Your typical Catwoman is that of clever thief with a heart-of-gold who you can never quite trust completely. It&amp;rsquo;s that characteristic, that she&amp;rsquo;s going to screw you in the end, that has followed the character around. For me at least it&amp;rsquo;s gotten a little stale; and because of that I can understand why some people feel like Catwoman isn&amp;rsquo;t a character that much can be done with. Lucky Brubaker puts that opinion to rest for good. This is a different Catwoman. There is no heart-of-gold here, she&amp;rsquo;s a geniunely good person who has a certain perspective that allows her to do bad things to people of a certain affluence and power. But to her peeps, those who grew up on the street like her, she&amp;rsquo;s somewhat of a Robin Hood figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series we see a half-reformed Catwoman. One who has turned to a life of charity and giving back to the place that made her who she is. But she always has one foot back in the life of anti-heroism, as she seeks to protect her neighborhood. That&amp;rsquo;s what makes the dynamic of this book so intriguing. We know that she&amp;rsquo;s going to remain Catwoman yet the woman that we see as Selina Kyle isn&amp;rsquo;t capable of becoming an out-and-out criminal. So she has to tip-toe the line. She is a vigilante, but a respectable one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-mask:40f7a85e8bc1401d841f5a423186f406&#34;&gt;Black Mask&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve read a &lt;strong&gt;Black Mask&lt;/strong&gt; story, not being aware of the character at all before picking up this trade. First thought was that he looks almost exactly like Red Skull, one of Captain America&amp;rsquo;s rogues, but the internet seems to suggest the characters aren&amp;rsquo;t much related aside from their looks. Black Mask is a crime boss, and that&amp;rsquo;s the gist of what I know about the character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately this series doesn&amp;rsquo;t get too much into his background or motivation. In one of the very last issues of the trade we get a little back story about what happened to him. It&amp;rsquo;s a creepy vignette about being tortured and how surviving it led him to embrace the mask and see torture as an art form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to worry though, this story is about Catwoman and how her past follows her into her present. Selina finds that a childhood friend, Sylvia Sinclair, has made her way back to Gotham, seemingly helping kids stay out of trouble. Later we found out that she is working for Black Mask; being used actually because she is one of the only people that know the true identity of Catwoman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catwoman is getting in Black Mask&amp;rsquo;s way, it&amp;rsquo;s as simple as that. However, it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting exploration into how Catwoman deals with the fact that her past causes hardship in her present, and how it affects those around her. Selina&amp;rsquo;s sister is badly traumatized in this storyline (her husband is tortured and murdered) and that follows the rest of the trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;selina-and-holly-road-trip-it:40f7a85e8bc1401d841f5a423186f406&#34;&gt;Selina and Holly Road Trip It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade drags a little after the Black Mask story completes with Selina, her sister, and Slam (who is an awesome character by the way) deal with the events that occurred in the previous story. There&amp;rsquo;s some good stuff here, and Slam and Selina&amp;rsquo;s relationship is revealing about both of their personalities; Selina wants a distraction whereas Slam wants something to anchor him to the real world. Ultimately though, aside from the gorgeous art, I felt that this middle section could have been left out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After, however, we get a series of wonderful stories involving Selina and Holly going on a road trip and the adventures that follow from that. Wildcat makes an appearance and becomes Holly&amp;rsquo;s trainer. Catwoman and Holly stumbling upon a robbery in a diner is my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I really want from a Catwoman series, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided. The 1 or 2 issue story arcs work well for the character as they allow her to explore the many sides of her personality, better. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that the 3rd trade continues with that, at least for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:40f7a85e8bc1401d841f5a423186f406&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trade did exactly what a good trade is supposed to do; left me wanting more, but feeling satisfied for what I got. To that end I&amp;rsquo;ve picked up volume 1, which features Brubaker along with Darwyn Cooke (who I&amp;rsquo;ve liked in nearly everything he&amp;rsquo;s done).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it stumbled just a little after the conclusion of the Black Mask story, it eventually turned into a series of smaller fun stories. I could have an ongoing of these types of Catwoman stories and you&amp;rsquo;d get no complaints out of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catwoman Volume 2 has made me rethink what is possible with characters who are seemingly one-dimensional. Brubaker tapped into the 60s aesthetic his artists gave him and used it to paint a wonderful tapestry of Selina Kyle living with his past and struggling to embrace the present. Is there any better compliment a writer can get?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>